Guide to the Burt Green Wilder papers, 1841-1925
Wilder, Burt Green papers, 1841-1925
- Photographs, Portraits of BGW's military and medical colleagues during the Civil War (original cabinet card photographs, unless otherwise noted); two small photos of Civil War battle sites in South Carolina; one record-book [Descriptive captions based on Wilder's own notes]
  - Sergt. Andrew Jackson Smith (African American) Co. B, 55th Mass.; saved the colors at Battle of Honey Hill, S.C., Nov. 30, 1864 (2 cc of same photo: picture postcard by Paschal Studio, Paducah, KY) (Box 19, Folder 45)
  - Geneva Smith Older daughter of Sergt. Andrew Jackson Smith when she was about 6 or 7 years ol picture postcard, by: Paschal Studio, Paducah, KY; 5.25" x 3.5" (Box 19, Folder 46)
  - Capt. Charles Carroll Soule Co. K, 55th Mass.; Brevet-major in U.S. Vols. Later, founder and head of the Boston Book Company, publisher of L. Emilio’s A Brave Black Regiment; died Jan. 7, 1913 (Box 19, Folder 47)
  - Mrs. Sarah J. Sprague, Lynn, Mass., formerly Miss Milliken, nurse in the eighth ward of Judiciary Square Hospital, Wash., DC, 1862-63 2 photos, ca. 1900-1910s, 7.0" x 5.0" (Box 19, Folder 48)
  - Frank E. Thayer Dedham, Mass.; at age 10 he had been BGW's "orderly" in action at River's Causeway; later a merchant in Springfield, Mass. Died July 6, 1911 4.75" x 5.0" (Box 19, Folder 49)
  - Capt. James Danforth Thurber (1839-1921) Co. F, 55th Mass.; Brevet Maj. of U.S. Vols.; wounded July 2, 1864; "A perfect soldier and gentleman" b. Feb. 21, 1839; d. Sept. 12, 1921 photo by: D. Hinkle, Germantown, PA; 6.5" x 4.25" (Box 19, Folder 50)
  - James O. Weil (1920) hospital patient of BGW in 1862 (Box 19, Folder 51)
  - Brig. Gen. Edward A, Wild commanded the brigade including the 55th during the first three months of its service; previously the Wilder family's physician photo by: F. T. Stuart, Boston; 6.75" x 5.75" (Box 19, Folder 52)
  - Burt Green Wilder, Surgeon in uniform, ca. 1865 three photos (plus a modern surrogate print of one) plus one Ambrotype, by Davis & Co., Boston (Box 19, Folder 53)
  - ____ Wing, Lieut. (Box 19, Folder 54)
  - unidentified officer, standing; has lost left arm (Box 19, Folder 55)
  - unidentified officer, seated photo by: Brady's National Photographic Portrait Galleries, New York and Washington, D.C.; 4.0" x 2.5" (Box 19, Folder 56)
  - unidentified officer 6.5” x 8.5” (Box 19, Folder 57)
  - Drs. John L. Craven and Samuel A. Green (and others), examining a wounded soldier in a hospital tent, summer of 1863, Morris Island, S.C. (Box 19, Folder 58)
  - trench near River's Causeway, S.C. trench used by Union army for refuge, July 2, 1864; photo taken spring 1895; 6.5" x 5.0" (Box 19, Folder 59)
  - Fort Lamar, the most easterly of the line of Confederate works on James Island, S.C., 6.5" x 5.0", 1895 (Box 19, Folder 60)
  - modern negatives of several prints in Box 19 (Box 19, Folder 61)
  - Record-book, containing ruled pages with signatures, annual meeting notes, treasurers’ reports, etc.: Association of Officers of the Fifty-Fifth Mass. Vol. Inftr’y ,1877, 1909 (Box 19, Folder 62)
  - Photographs (primarily cabinet cards, but also some tintypes) (Box 20)
  - Burt Green Wilder (several photos, mostly cabinet cards) (Box 20)
  - Celia Colton Burt (1812-1904), BGW's mother, photo in later life (Box 20)
  - David Wilder, Sr. (1809-1891), BGW's father, photo in later life (Box 20)
  - Sarah Cowell Nichols, BGW's first wife: solo portrait (between 1874-1884); with eldest daughter, Ruth (Box 20)
  - Dr. William Nichols, BGW's father-in-law (Box 20)
  - Ruth Wilder, eldest daughter, who died before reaching one year: Oct. 29, 1869 (at 7 1/2 mos.); several undated; just after she died (Box 20)
  - Mary Nichols Wilder (b. 1871? second daughter): cabinet card photos of her as an infant, little girl, and young woman also, 10 tintypes, probably of Mary, including one with her as little girl with an African American woman, probably a nanny (Box 20)
  - Bertha Wilder, youngest daughter (b. 1874): as an infant; little girl; as a teenager playing the violin; as a young woman (Box 20)
  - BGW and his second wife, Mary Field Wilder, 1919 at Siasconset ("Sconset") Nantucket, with BGW's note: "ourselves & 'Gray Brother Jr.' [cat] taken by Juanita Bates at close of her visit here in spring of 1919" (Box 20)
  - Wilder Breckenridge (1899-1976): two photos: one cabinet card dated Feb. 1901 (at 19 months); one portrait, dated 1915 (at age 16) grandson of BGW: son of Mary N. Wilder and Roeliff Morton Breckenridge, '92, Cornell Class of 1919 brother of Hugh, '26, and brother-in-law, via sister Anne, of Mordelo Lee Vincent, Jr., '26 (Box 20)
  - David Wilder, Jr. (BGW's brother, b. 1837) and his wife (Box 20)
  - Edward Wilder (BGW's brother, b. 1843) (Box 20)
  - Mabel Scott Wilder (b. 1869), daughter of Edward Wilder (in group photo with her two brothers, as young children; photo by Imperial, San Francisco: see two below) (Box 20)
  - Edward Twichell Wilder (1872-1929), '93, son of Edward Wilder (see above) (Box 20)
  - Walter Robb Wilder (1875-1934), '96, son of Edward Wilder (see above) (Box 20)
  - Mary Catherine Scott Wilder (?--unidentified, but very possibly wife of Edward Wilder (photo by Imperial, San Francisco; she resembles Mabel Scott Wilder in photo above) (Box 20)
  - Sophronia Wilder Edgerly (1823-1915), in 1880 at age 57; BGW's paternal aunt (youngest child of his grandparents David Wilder and Sally Nourse Butler) (Box 20)
  - BGW's cousins: young children of Sophronia Wilder and James Wheeler Edgerly: 9 miniature tintypes, four of which identified only by first name only one tintype has complete name: William Drew Edgerly (1866-1869) (Box 20)
  - Mary Nichols Barnard, sister of Sarah Nichols Wilder (Box 20)
  - William Nichols Barnard, '97 (1875-1947), as young boy; son of Mary Nichols Barnard and William Stebbins Barnard, '71. Cornell Prof. of Mechanical Engineering; became Director of Sibley School of Engineering in 1938 (Box 20)
  - Group portrait of little boy, older boy, and little girl, with note on verso: "Aunt Mamie with best love from Dick, Sister & Harry, Jan 1st 1881" (Boston) (Box 20)
  - Tintype, ca. 2-3": unidentified African-American man, standing; holds a cabinet card photo of an unidentified bearded white man (photo by R. L. Wood, Canal St., NYC) (Box 20)
  - Four small cartes-de-visite: friends and/or family: Jessie G. Dart, New London, CT, Barbara M. Ringeling, April 1874, Staten Island, Charles H. Robinson, of Nantucket, "who built my cottage at Sciasconset ….", Mrs. Vincent, Boston Museum (Box 20)
  - Two snapshots, both dated 1914, with BGW's notes: "Dr. Edw. Cranch and family, 813 Sassafras St., Erie, Pa. 6 sons, 1 daughter, 10 grandchildren"; "Dr. Edw. Cranch's children: Charles, Gerard, Raymond, Walter, Eliot, Edith, Eugene" [ages 20-37] (Box 20)
  - Snapshot taken at Woodlawn Cemetery, May 30, 1921, by E??. Flagg: Mrs. Alice Field Dudley of Newton Centre; Mr. Isaac Sprague of Wellesley, Mass.; Mr. Edward Dudley of Newton Centre; Mr. Edward H. Flagg and Mr. Walter E. Flagg of Wellesley; soldier not known (Box 20)
  - 3 cabinet card photos: unidentified young women (at least two were possible brain donors): (Box 20)
  - Photo by J. Notman, Boston, w. BGW's notation, verso upper right: "4629" (brain no.?) (Box 20)
  - Photo by J. Notman, Boston, w. BGW's notation, verso upper right: "4675" (brain no.?) (Box 20)
  - With spectacles; photo by Pach Bros., Cambridge, Mass., "19641" noted by ?, verso lower right (Box 20)
  - Katharine Kemp-Stillings, violinist two printed photos of her as a young woman, in a brochure about her; w. BGW's note that "we lived in her mother's house on Park St., Brookline" (Box 20)
  - George Washington Meacham (b. 1827), at age 83, picture postcard, from Idah Meacham Strobridge, Los Angeles, who writes: "A California Pioneer of 1849 …" (friend or colleague of BGW?), 1910 (Box 20)
  - Two houses: "Grandfather's house at Leominster, Mass.; return to Mrs. Marshalt, occupying it"; "Pringle Mansion, King St. Charleston, S.C. April 1913" (Box 20)
  - Photographs of Burt Green Wilder's students (their class years given, when known); Cornell faculty colleagues; non-Cornell colleagues, primarily zoologists, anatomists, neurologists, physicians, etc. (some of whose correspondence is elsewhere in the collection); other persons identified by name but lacking attribution; some brain donors (Box 21)
  - Louis Agassiz and Count De Pourtales (Boston) (Box 21)
  - Major W. E. Arnold, Military Science, Cornell (Box 21)
  - (Box 21)
  - Fordyce Barker (with autograph) (Box 21)
  - Bischoff [probably Theodor L. W. Bischoff, 1807-1882, anatomist, neurologist] (Box 21)
  - Wm. (?) Bourland (Box 21)
  - William E.(?) Browning, March 1889 (Box 21)
  - Prof. H. Carmichael (Portland, Me.) (Box 21)
  - Major Louis Cazione, Bowdoin College, Brunswick, Me. (Box 21)
  - Prof. H. L. Chapman (Boston) (Box 21)
  - James Bertram Clarke, Cornell Class of 1910 (with autograph) African-American student; member of Alpha Phi Alpha BGW’s note: “One of the best men and most brilliant scholars graduated from Cornell University. He is now connected with the Crisis in New York.” (Box 21)
  - Dr. Eugene Rollin Corson (1855-1946); Cornell Class of 1875 2 photos from Ithaca: by Beardsley; by Evans son of Prof. Hiram Corson (Box 21)
  - Benjamin E. Cotting, Curator of the Lowell Institute (with autograph) (Box 21)
  - Hosea Curtice (1825-1893), with BGW's note: "Brain 3091" American mathematician and educator; donor to BGW's brain collection See: Dept. of Zoology records (# 14-26-966), Box 17, which contains Accession Book, 1882-1897 (record of specimens received): specimen no. 3091, Hosea Curtice of Moravia, NY, was received June 13, 1893, from his son, Dr. (Fred) Cooper Curtice, Cornell Class of 1881 (Box 21)
  - James D(wight) Dana, 1889 (Box 21)
  - Orville A. Derby, Cornell Class of 1873 (with autograph) (Box 21)
  - DuBois Raymond, [Emil du Bois-Raymond (1818-1896), German physician and physiologist)], 1872 (Box 21)
  - Arthur M. Edwards, M.D., Newark, NJ; BGW notes to see his letter about brain bequest, June, 1897 (Box 21)
  - Pierre A. Fish, Cornell Prof. Veterinary Physiology; 2 photos (Box 21)
  - Horace Howard Furness, Philadelphia (Box 21)
  - Simon H. Gage; 3 photos, 1877, 1889, 1890 (Box 21)
  - Carl Gegenbaur (1826-1903), Morphologist; 2 photos (Box 21)
  - Gilder [American poet and editor Richard Watson Gilder, 1844-1909] (Box 21)
  - Benjamin Apthorpe Gould, PhD, ca. 1865 (Box 21)
  - Ernst Haeckel, 1872 (Box 21)
  - Alfredo Gottlieb Hammar, Cornell Class of 1907 (Agr.), 1907 student of BGW (Box 21)
  - Oliver Wendell Holmes (1809-1894), poet and physician carte-de-visite, 1865 (at age 56); printed (not original) photo, ca. 1880 (Box 21)
  - Grant Sherman Hopkins, Cornell Class of 1889 (BS), DSc 1893, DVM 1900 also CU Prof. of Veterinary Anatomy (Box 21)
  - G. M. Humphrey, Cambridge (Box 21)
  - Thomas H. Huxley, 1876 (Box 21)
  - J. B. S. Jackson (Boston pathologist, d. 1879) (Box 21)
  - Joe Jefferson (Box 21)
  - David Starr Jordan (1851-1931); Cornell Class of 1872; 2 photos (Box 21)
  - Dr. W. W. Keen, Philadelphia (Box 21)
  - Koelliker [probably Albert Koelliker, 1817-1905] (Box 21)
  - Dr. W. C. (William Christopher) Krauss, Buffalo, NY; Cornell Class of 1884 with autograph note to BGW (Box 21)
  - Leuckart (?), Leipzig [probably Rudolf Leuckart (1822-1898), German zoologist and parasitologist] (Box 21)
  - Henry B. Lord (1821-1915), CU Trustee from 1876-1915; photo by George C. Stanley Gallery, Ithaca March 1906 (Box 21)
  - Augustus Nathaniel Hubert Lushington, Med. Prep. Spec., Cornell 1889-94 (African descent; originally from Trinidad) became veterinarian in Lynchburg, VA (Box 21)
  - Dr. Anita Newcomb McGee (1864-1940), w. autograph Acting Ass't Surgeon in the U.S. Army; founder of the Army Nurse Corps mother of Donald McGee, whose brain she donated to BGW after he died at the age of 9 months [photo of Donald alive accompanies his mother's letters to BGW, in Box 2-1], June 1894 (Box 21)
  - Dr. Alfred Mitchell, Brunswick, Me. (of Bowdoin College?) (Box 21)
  - S(ilas) Weir Mitchell, M.D. (Box 21)
  - St. George Mivart (St. George Jackson Mivart), 1827-1900, anatomist (Box 21)
  - Joseph Moore, Earlham College, Richmond, Ind. (seated, bearded older man) (Box 21)
  - Veranus A. Moore, M.D., March 20, 1880 (Box 21)
  - Nathaniel Allison Murray, Cornell Class of 1911 (with autograph) African-American student; one of Alpha Phi Alpha’s seven Jewels (Box 21)
  - Andrew Newell, San Francisco (Box 21)
  - R. Owen (Sir Richard Owen) (Box 21)
  - T(homas) Jeffery [sic] Parker, author of *Text-bok of zoology* (1897), February 1893 (Box 21)
  - W(illiam) Kitchen Parker, father of T. Jeffery Parker and William Newton Parker author of *Morphology of the skull*, 1877 (Box 21)
  - Charles G. Pease, M.D., New York (with autograph) (Box 21)
  - Milton Josiah Roberts, Cornell Class of 1875; died 1893; 2 photos, Prof. of Orthopedic Surgery, University of Vermont), 1891 (Box 21)
  - Dr. D. A. Robinson, Bangor, Me. (Box 21)
  - George Rolleston, Prof. at Oxford (two photos, incl. one small) (Box 21)
  - Max Gustav Schlapp, Cornell Class of 1893 (Special Course) physician in New York (Box 21)
  - Edward Anthony Spitzka (1876-1922), anatomist, neurologist (printed, not original photo; w. printed signature) (Box 21)
  - Edward Charles Spitzka (1852-1914), anatomist, neurologist (father of Edw. Anthony) (Box 21)
  - Homer B. Sprague, (photo by Purdy & Frear, Ithaca; student or faculty or other Ithacan?), March 29, 1869 (Box 21)
  - Mr. Elmer Stilwell Janitor of Dept. of Zoology, McGraw Hall (Box 21)
  - T. B. (Thomas Blanchard) Stowell, Chair of Natural Sciences at Cortland State Normal School, 1869-1889 (Box 21)
  - Thomas Blanchard Stowell and Mary Blakeslee Stowell: Cortland, NY 1869; Potsdam, NY 1894; Los Angeles, Calif. 1919; 3 small cameo, non-original photos of each, printed on single sheet; w. BGW's note on verso: "We made their acquaintance in 1873-4 at the Agassiz (Anderson) "Summer School of Natural History" on Penikese Id., near New Bedford …", 1869, 1894, 1919 (Box 21)
  - Senator Charles Sumner of Massachusetts (1811-1874), abolitionist (Box 21)
  - Henry Ward Turner, Philadelphia, February 23, 1881 (Box 21)
  - John Tyndall (?) (small engraving) (Box 21)
  - (Rudolf) Virchow (Berlin), 1872 (Box 21)
  - Booker T. Washington (not original photo; in newspaper clipping at time of his death), 1915 (Box 21)
  - Millard Welfman (?), Boston (Box 21)
  - Prof. S. A. White (Peoria, Ill.) (Box 21)
  - Solon F. Whitney (photo of painted portrait) assistant teacher at Brookline, Mass. school, at time BGW was there (Box 21)
  - Harris Hawthorne Wilder (1864-1928) Prof. of Zoology at Smith College (founded the dept. there in 1894) amphibians; evolution; comparative anatomy; anthropometry (Box 21)
  - Chauncey Wright (2 photos) (Box 21)
  - Dr. Jeffries Wyman, Sr.(?) (2 photos, one dated May 1868) (Box 21)
  - "Roster of Commissioned Officers of the 55th Regiment Mass. Vol. Infantry 1863-1865." Photo album compiled by Burt Green Wilder (Box 24)
    This list replaces an earlier typed list that neither included names of officers whose photos are lacking, nor identified African-American officers, nor provided page numbers. A note on the earlier list says: "Orig. List sent to National Archives, 1961." Names are listed in the order in which they appear in the album, followed by the page number; lacking photos are noted.
    This list indicates African-American officers, including those whose photos are lacking. To confirm which officers (including those lacking photos) were African- American, the following website was consulted: http://suvcw.org/mollus/usctofficers.htm ( U.S. Commissioned Officers of African-American Descent who served during the Civil War). [SUVCW stands for Sons of Union Veterans of the Civil War; MOLLUS for Military Order of the Loyal Legion of the United States; and USCT for United States Colored Troops]. Where photo is lacking, or where given information is possibly uncertain, the designation [African-American] indicates confirmation via this website. Please note that the website list may be incomplete, so not all officers lacking photos in the album are fully identified.
    Individual companies of the 55th are indicated for each person, when known, and/or the person's rank/membership in other army divisions, when known; This list does not record the complete military history accompanying each photo.
    Photos of some of the persons in the album appear elsewhere (loose) in the collection, as indicated in the guide; some of these additional photos are duplicates, while others are post-war; Wilder wrote captions on many of them.
    Letters to Wilder from some of these officers, and/or references to these officers, appear elsewhere in the collection.
    All photos in the album are 4.0" x 2.5" cabinet cards; photographer/ studio is given when available.
    - Col. Norwood Penrose Hallowell, 1 (Box 24)
    - Col. Alfred Stedman Hartwell, 2 (Box 24)
    - Lieut. Col. Charles Barnard Fox (photo by Whipple, Boston), 3 (Box 24)
    - Lieut. Col William Nutt, 4 (Box 24)
    - Major Sigourney Wales, 5 (Box 24)
    - Maj. Wheelock Pratt, 6 (Box 24)
    - William Symmington Brown, Surgeon (Black & Case, Boston), 7 (Box 24)
    - Burt Green Wilder, Surgeon, 8 (Box 24)
    - Chaplain William Jackson: photo lacking; [African-American], 9 (Box 24)
    - Chaplain John R. Bowles (African-American; F. A. Simonds, Chillicothe, Ohio), 10 (Box 24)
    - Capt. Robert James Hamilton (Co. G), 11 (Box 24)
    - Capt. William Dwight Crane (Co. H), 12 (Box 24)
    - Capt. Charles Carroll Soule (Co. K), 13 (Box 24)
    - Capt. Charles Edward Grant (Co. B), 14 (Box 24)
    - Capt. John Gordon (Co. I), 15 (Box 24)
    - Capt. Charles Pickering Bowditch (Co. A; Capt. 5th Mass. Cav.), 16 (Box 24)
    - Capt. Frank Goodwin (Brevet Major, U.S. Vols.; Warren, Cambridgeport, Mass.), 17 (Box 24)
    - Capt. James Danforth Thurber (Brevet Major, U.S. Vols.; A. H. Locke, Plymouth, Mass.), 18 (Box 24)
    - Capt. William Haviland Torrey (Co. C; Brevet Major, U.S. Vols.), 19 (Box 24)
    - Capt. George Moore Woodward (Co. A), 20 (Box 24)
    - Capt. George Frederick McKay (Co. C; Brevet Major, U.S. Vols.), 21 (Box 24)
    - Capt. Thomas Foldes Ellsworth (Co. H), 22 (Box 24)
    - Capt. Josiah C. Hall (Co. D), 23 (Box 24)
    - Capt. George Thompson Garrison (Co. I; Brevet Major, U.S. Vols.), 24 (Box 24)
    - Capt. Nathaniel Eustace Ladd (Co. H; Brevet Major, U.S. Vols.; Whipple, Boston), 25 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. and Qr. M. George B. Mussey: photo lacking, 26 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. and Adjt. William Penrose Hallowell, 27 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. Edward Stearns Stimpson, 28 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. Dennis Hartwell Jones (J. S. Black, Boston), 29 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. Harrison Holt (A. Lonrel, Boston), 30 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. Wyllys Gannett, 31 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. and Qr. M. John Osborne Mowry (O. C. Knox, Athol Depot, Mass.), 32 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. Ephraim Albert Wood (J. W. Black, Boston), 33 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. Robertson James (Brevet Capt.; Black & Case, Boston), 34 (Box 24)
    - Asst. Surgeon Warren Morris Babbitt: photo lacking, 35 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. Ezekiel Fowler: photo lacking, 36 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. Winthrop Perkins Boynton, 37 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. Leonard Battelle Perry (Capt. & A.A.G. Vols.), 38 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. Thomas Leader Harman (Whipple, Boston), 39 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. Alphonso Marsh (Moulton ,Fitchburg, Mass.), 40 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. William C. Roberts (Brevet Capt., U.S. Vols.), 41 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. Josiah A. Bean (Brevet Capt., U.S. Vols.), 42 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. E. Harris Jewett, 43 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. Henry Newton Sheldon, 44 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. Peter N. Sprague (L. W. Cook, Weymouth Landing, Mass.), 45 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. and Adjt. Charles W. Mutell: photo lacking, 46 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. Charles L. Roberts (Frank Rowell, Boston), 47 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. Solomon C. Starbird (Black & Case, Boston), 48 (Box 24)
    - William H. Lathrop, Asst. Surgeon (G. Grellings, Detroit), 49 (Box 24)
    - 1st Lieut. George H. Carter: photo lacking, 50 (Box 24)
    - 2nd Lieut. Leonard Case Alden (Black & Case, Boston), 51 (Box 24)
    - 2nd Lieut. John H. Kingston, 52 (Box 24)
    - 2nd Lieut. William Dorance Messinger: photo lacking, 53 (Box 24)
    - 2nd Lieut. Joseph Towne Nichols: photo lacking, 54 (Box 24)
    - 2nd Lieut. Ezra P. Gould (Major, 59th Mass. Vols.; Warren, Cambridgeport, Mass.), 55 (Box 24)
    - 2nd Lieut. Albert Henry Bradish (Fisher Bros., Boston), 56 (Box 24)
    - 2nd Lieut. Edwin Ruthen Hill (Taylor & Preston, Salem, Mass.), 57 (Box 24)
    - 2nd Lieut. Charles F. Lee (Brevet 1st Lieut, U.S. Vols.; J. C. Spooner's Picture Palace, Springfield, Mass.), 58 (Box 24)
    - 2nd Lieut. George A. Glidden: photo lacking, 59 (Box 24)
    - 2nd Lieut. Marshall E. Hunter (H. O. Foster, Charleston, S.C.), 60 (Box 24)
    - 2nd Lieut. John Freeman Shorter (African-American; Biddle, Photographer, Xenia, Ohio), 61 (Box 24)
    - 2nd Lieut. James Monroe Trotter (African-American), 62 (Box 24)
    - 2nd Lieut. William H. Dupree (African-American; F. A. Simonds, Chillicothe, Ohio), 63 (Box 24)
    - Sergt. Charles L. Mitchell (2nd Lieut., 55th Mass. Vols.; Prescott Whiting, Boston) [African-American], 64 (Box 24)
    - Sergt. Abram W. Shadd (African-American; 2nd Lieut., 55th Mass. Vols.; Brady's National Photographic Portrait, New York), 65 (Box 24)
    - Com. Sergt. Richard M. White: photo lacking; [African-American], 66 (Box 24)
    - Qr. M. Sergt. Martin F. Becker (born in Africa, 1834): photo lacking; [African-American], 67 (Box 24)
    - 1st Sergt. Armstead M. Jones: photo lacking; [African-American], 68 (Box 24)
- Items removed from the collection.
  There are several other Wilder items that have been cataloged individually outside of this collection. This is just a partial listing.
  - Book: Official Records of Union and Confederate Armies (Washington: GPO, 1891) prepared by the late Lt. Col. Robert N. Scott, 3rd US Art., Series I, Vol. 35 - in 2 parts, part 1, now cataloged as Rare E491 U58 Ser.1,v.35,pt.1
  - Scrapbook including hygiene and other loose printed material. [See also CUL-CUF, bound volumes Wilder "Papers 1882-1911" "Miscellaneous Pamphlets 15"] now cataloged as Rare QL3.W55